What are some of the most common side
effects you see on guys starting TRT? Is
that high blood pressure, anxiety? I
don't know.
The major side effects of TRT. Number
one, you can't really have this
discussion without mentioning it is
infertility. Most men, especially on
injectable testosterone, but even on
compounded creams, their sperm counts
will go way down. A lot of them will
develop what's called auspermia meaning
they won't have really
they'll be infertile. Okay. Um which is
largely reversible by the way or and
treatable and preventable with other
medications but that is the most common
side effect is some degree of
infertility. Another side effect is
edema or what we call water retention.
The water retention that comes with
testosterone and other androgens is
quite annoying because from what I can
tell it's not always like a gravity
dependent thing. So a lot of people
after they work all day they notice
their legs are are swollen. You know
they develop what's called pitting
edema. So they press on their ankle bone
you'll see like an indentation. You know
it's a indication of a lot of water in
your extracellular space so to speak. So
testosterone can worsen that. But
testosterone even can do things like
bloat your face, you know, make you get
water retention in your face. And we
don't know all the reasons why
testosterone does that. If you look in
textbooks, they'll mention a bunch of
different mechanisms that have never
been proven. Um, but that so that is a
symptom, a potential symptom. Cognitive
symptoms. You asked about anxiety. The
thing we see most commonly is what we
what we would say is mood liability
which is not necessarily anxiety or
depression but moods that fluctuate
rapidly. Okay. Um so that could mean for
certain patients they have much more
anxiety. That could mean for some
patients they experience a degree of
euphoria. Actually both of those are
side effects. It's not good to get
either of them. Um but uh can it happen?
It it can and it does happen. Sexual
dysfunction can be a transient side
effect to people starting testosterone.
They can feel like their libido is lower
or that it's good some days, bad some
days. That typically resolves after 3
months. Same with any interransient
erectile function issues. Um increased
red blood cells if you want to call that
a side effect that you know obviously
that happens in many patients. Um acne
definitely can be worsened by um by
androgens. Um there it testosterone can
worsen sleep apnea too if it's
untreated.
It causes a component of central apnea.
So actually technically it's unclear
whether it actually worsens the
obstructive component of the apnea
meaning how many times you have like
hypopnic episodes where you don't fully
breathe you know you don't get a full
oxygenated breath I guess would be the
way to say it. Um but it does cause a
temporary worsening of your overall
sleep architecture by uh causing uh a
central sleep apnea component. And in
two studies that effect is goes away
after about or is undetectable after
about 18 months. Um and then the last
thing is well there's two more things.
Worsening male pattern hair loss. never
really been proven that testosterone
worsens that. In theory, it could though
because male pattern hair loss is at
least in very large part a DHT driven
process. And remember from testosterone,
you get estradile, you get DHT. So maybe
by raising your DHT levels that can
worsen your hair loss. What I'll say is
that some men actually grow hair on
testosterone on their scalp. It's a
minority, but some do. There's a very
complex relationship between low
testosterone and scalp levels of
hormones such that some men, most men I
would say won't really affect things
like you're going to lose your hair
anyway just because of your genetics if
you don't do anything about it. Some men
maybe it accelerates it. Some actually
grow hair weirdly and weirdly or not.
The last thing is gynecomastia.
Gynecomastia is where you get uh
glandular breast tissue under your
nipple and specifically under your
nipple. Usually it's a nodule that you
can feel it's like mobile and it's often
very painful too. So it's not like my
you know my I [snorts] have what I call
tits or whatever. Um it's really
it's a glandular breast tissue that you
can feel and it's it's like present
there. You can even detect it on mam
mimography or cut it out in surgery. So,
and that's potential. Those are all the
common side effects.